Guide to the George Jarvis Brush Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Correspondence, 1850-1907, 1909-1912, 1914, 1916-1920, 1924, 1932, 1939, 1960, undated; Series I; 3' (7 boxes)
  - George Jarvis Brush
    - P (20), 1859-1860, 1862-1866, 1868-1869, 1874, 1876, 1884, 1911, undated (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Park, James Jr. (2), 1864 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Pearse, John Barnard S. (1), 1868 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Peirce, Benjamin (1809-1880) (1), 1871 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Penfield, Samuel L. (1), 1900 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Percy, John (5), 1859, 1863, 1868, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Phelps, Edward John (1), 1886 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Phelps, William Walter (4), 1874, 1886, 1891, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Pirsson, Louis Valentine (2), 1897, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Pisani, Felix (4), 1857, 1866, 1868, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Porter, John Addison (2), 1860-1861 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Porter, Noah (1), 1885 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Prudden, Theophil Mitchell (1), 1875 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Pumpelly, Raphael (6), 1866, 1872, 1875, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - R (9), 1855, 1866-1868, 1875-1876, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Ramsay, Sir Andrew Crombie (5), 1857, 1859, 1864, 1872, 1874 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Ramsay, Louisa, Lady (1), 1879 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Rath, Gerhard von (4), 1884-1887 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Raymond, Rossiter Worthington (1), 1869 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Rice, William North (1), 1875 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Richter, Hieronymus Theodore (3), 1868, 1869, 1872 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Robbins, James Watson (1), 1862 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Rockwell, Alfred Perkins (7), 1857-1858, 1860, 1863, 1867, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Roepper, William Theodore (59), 1858-1867, 1869-1870, 1875, 1878-1879, undated (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Rogers, William Barton (2), 1865, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Rood, Ogden Nicholas (25), 1856, 1860-1864, 1872, 1875, 1880, 1882, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Root, Edward Warren (4), 1867-1868 (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Root, Oren (7), 1862-1863, 1867, 1875, 1881 (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Roscoe, Sir Henry Enfield (4), 1884, 1907, undated (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - S (31), 1852, 1858-1859, 1860, 1862, 1864, 1866-1868, 1872, 1875, 1877, 1886 (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Saemann, Louis (7), 1854, 1858, 1861-1864 (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Sampson, Joseph (1), 1867 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Schuchert, Charles (1), 1911 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Seelye, Julius Hawley (1), 1877 (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - Seymour, Edward (6), 1855, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - Sheffield, Charles Joseph (1), 1868 (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Sheffield, Joseph Earl (1), undated (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Sheffield Scientific School, Board of Trustees (1), 1904 (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Shepard, Charles Upham (5), 1855, 1859, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Shipman, Nathaniel (3), 1862-1863, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, Jr. (8), 1862-1864, 1867, 1869, undated (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, Sr. (4), 1853-1855, 1861, 1863 (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - Silliman, Susan Huldah (Forbes) (1), 1870 (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - Smith, John Lawrence (60), 1853-1856, 1858, 1860-1867, 1869-1870, 1872, 1874, undated (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Smyth, Warington Wilkinson (6), 1868, 1874, 1876-1877, 1886, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Stanton, Frederick Perry (1), 1866 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Steinwehr, Adolf von (2), 1864-1865 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Stone, Amasa (1), 1865 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Storer, Francis Humphreys (16), 1862-1864, 1867-1868, undated (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Sumner, William Graham (1), 1881 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - T (9), 1862-1863, 1871, 1887 (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Tatham, Charles B. (4), 1859, 1864-1865 (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - Taylor, William J. (39), 1858-1864 (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - Torrey, John (7), 1862-1863, 1866, 1869 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Trautwine, John Cresson (12), 1858-1859, 1861, 1864, 1869, 1871, 1875, 1878 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Trowbridge, William Petit (1), 1870 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Trumbull, James Hammond (1), 1863 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Trumbull, Lyman (6), 1865-1867, 1869, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Tschermak, Gustav (3), 1869, 1871-1872 (Box 5, Folder 133)
    - Tufts, Charles A. (5), 1864 (Box 5, Folder 133)
    - Tyndall, John (1), 1873 (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Ulrich, Franz (1), 1890 (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Vaux, William Sandys Wright (2), 1859, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Verrill, Addison Emery (2), 1864 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Vroom, Peter Dumont (1), 1854 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - W (23), 1859, 1861, 1863-1864, 1866-1867, 1872, 1879, 1882, 1892, 1899, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Walker, Francis Amasa (13), 1872, 1878, 1881-1882, 1888, 1893, 1896 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Wall, George Parkes (3), 1859-1860 (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Wappler, Benno (2), 1857-1858 (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Ward, Henry Augustus (1), 1862 (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Warren, Cyrus Moors (1), 1864 (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Wayland, F. (2), 1855, 1858 (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - Weisbach, Albin (5), 1884-1885, 1887 (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Weld, Mason Cogsell (7), 1853-1854, 1858-1859 (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Westernmann and Co. (8), 1860, 1863-1864, 1867, 1869 (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Weyman, George Washington (6), 1857-1861 (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - Wharton, Joseph (77), 1860-1869, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Whitney, Josiah Dwight (43), 1860-1864, 1866, 1868, 1870, 1875 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Whitney, William Dwight (7), 1860, 1866, 1868, 1875, 1881, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Wiley, John (5), 1863-1864 (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Wiley, William Halstead (1), 1891 (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Willey, Joseph Edgerton (5), 1860, 1866, 1874 (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - Williams, Henry Shaler (1), 1873 (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - Woolsey, Theodore Dwight (5), 1877, 1887, undated (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - Worthen, Amos Henry (6), 1861, 1865, 1868 (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - Wurtz, Henry (21), 1854, 1857-1858, 1862, 1864, 1866-1867, undated (Box 5, Folder 151)
    - Zell, T. Elwood and Co. (4), 1862-1864, 1866 (Box 5, Folder 152)
    - Zepharovich, Victor Leopold (1), 1860 (Box 5, Folder 153)
    - Zepharovich, Madame Victor L. (1), 1890 (Box 5, Folder 153)
    - Zeuner, Gustav Anton (1), 1855 (Box 5, Folder 154)
    - Zschau, E. (1), 1854 (Box 5, Folder 155)
  - Harriet Silliman Brush
    - Cook, Burton Chauncey (1), 1862 (Box 6, Folder 156)
    - Dana, Henrietta Francis (Silliman) (55), 1851-1856, 1858-1859 (Box 6, Folder 157)
    - Dana, Henrietta Francis (Silliman) (62), 1860-1864 (Box 6, Folder 158)
    - Eliot, Charles William (1), 1898 (Box 6, Folder 159)
    - Fessenden, William Pitt (3), 1861 (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Grimes, Elizabeth Sarah (Nealley) (22), 1860-1862 (Box 6, Folder 161)
    - Grimes, Elizabeth Sarah (Nealley) (23), 1863-1864, 1866, 1868, 1871, 1873, 1875, 1885, 1887-1889, undated (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - Jayne, Ellen (1), 1861 (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - Marshall, Caroline Ward (Trumbull) (1), 1861 (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, Jr. (1), 1861 (Box 6, Folder 164)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, Sr. (1), 1862 (Box 6, Folder 164)
    - Stevens, J.H.D. (1), 1863 (Box 6, Folder 165)
    - Trumbull, Eliza (Bruyn) (1), 1857 (Box 6, Folder 165)
    - Trumbull, Jane Lathrop (7), 1861 (Box 6, Folder 166)
    - Trumbull, John (1), 1856 (Box 6, Folder 166)
    - Trumbull, Julia Maria (Jayne) (8), 1861-1862 (Box 6, Folder 167)
    - Trumbull, Lyman (13), 1859, 1861-1864 (Box 6, Folder 167)
  - Sarah Jarvis (Brush) McLaughlin(1)
    - Farnum, William W. (1), 1912 (Box 6, Folder 168)
    - James, Henry (1), 1930 (Box 6, Folder 168)
    - Trumbull, Lyman (1), 1892 (Box 6, Folder 168)
  - Eliza Trumbull (Brush) Pirsson
    - Eliot, Charles W. (1), 1924 (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - Pierson, George W. (1), 1939 (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - Stanley-Brown, Joseph (1), 1932 (Box 6, Folder 169)
  - Louis Valentine Pirsson
    - A,D,E,F,J,N,R (10), 1893-1897, 1916, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 170)
    - Adams, Frank Dawson (7), 1893, 1895-1897, 191 (Box 6, Folder 171)
    - Andreae, Achilles (1), 1894 (Box 6, Folder 171)
    - Bäckström, Helge Mattias (7), 1892-1893, 1895-1897 (Box 6, Folder 172)
    - Ballard, Harlan H. (1), 1897 (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - Barrois, Charles Eugene (1), 1918 (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - Becker, Charles Ferdinand (2), 1896 (Box 6, Folder 174)
    - Brögger, Waldemar Christopher (1), 1895 (Box 6, Folder 174)
    - Clark, William Bullock (3), 1894 (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - Clarke, Frank Wigglesworth (4), 1896-1897 (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - Clements, Julius Morgan (7), 1893-1896 (Box 6, Folder 176)
    - Cross, Whitman (29), 1893-1897 (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - Cross, Whitman (28), 1902-1907, 1909-1910, 1914, undated (Box 6, Folder 178)
    - Dana, James Dwight (5), 1893-1894 (Box 6, Folder 179)
    - Derby, Orville Adelbert (3), 1896 (Box 6, Folder 179)
    - Diller, Joseph Silas (4), 1894, 1896, 1903 (Box 7, Folder 180)
    - Ferrier, W.F. (2), 1896-1897 (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - Fouqué, Ferdinand André, 1895-1896 (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - Frosterus, Benjamin (3), 1892-1893, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - Genth, Frederick Augustus (2), 1891 (Box 7, Folder 182)
    - Goldschmidt, Victor (2), 1895 (Box 7, Folder 182)
    - Grant, Ulysses Sherman (2), 1895-1896 (Box 7, Folder 183)
    - Grinnell, George Bird (1), 1896 (Box 7, Folder 183)
    - Groth, Paul Heinrich (2), 1895 (Box 7, Folder 184)
    - Grout, Frank Fitch (1), 1919 (Box 7, Folder 184)
    - Hague, Arnold (1), 1897 (Box 7, Folder 185)
    - Harker, Alfred (1), 1919 (Box 7, Folder 185)
    - Hillebrand, William Francis (2), 1897 (Box 7, Folder 185)
    - Hobbs, William Herbert (2), 1895, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 186)
    - Hoffmann, G.C. (2), 1894 (Box 7, Folder 186)
    - Irving, John Duer (2), 1917-1918 (Box 7, Folder 187)
    - Kemp, James Furman (5), 1893-1895 (Box 7, Folder 188)
    - Kunz, George Frederick (1), 1896 (Box 7, Folder 188)
    - Lacroix, Alfred (5), 1891, 1893-1894, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 189)
    - Lawson, Andrew C. (1), 1896 (Box 7, Folder 189)
    - Leconte, Joseph (1), 1896 (Box 7, Folder 190)
    - Lindgren, Waldemar (1), 1895 (Box 7, Folder 190)
    - Merrill, George P. (2), 1895, undated (Box 7, Folder 191)
    - Pratt, Joseph H. (1), 1879 (Box 7, Folder 192)
    - Ransome, Frederick Lewis (1), 1897 (Box 7, Folder 193)
    - Rosenbusch, Harry (7), 1892, 1895-1896, 1905 (Box 7, Folder 193)
    - Sears, J.H. (1), 1895 (Box 7, Folder 194)
    - Szabo, Joseph (1), 1893 (Box 7, Folder 194)
    - Teall, Jethro Justinian Harris (6), 1896, 1911, 1914, 1916, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 195)
    - Thomas, Herbert Henry (1), 1914 (Box 7, Folder 195)
    - Washington, Henry Stephens (19), 1893-1897, 1918, undated (Box 7, Folder 196)
    - Weed, Walter Harvey (40), 1893-1896 (Box 7, Folder 197)
    - Weed, Walter Harvey (24), 1896-1897 (Box 7, Folder 198)
    - Wells, Horace. (1), 1897 (Box 7, Folder 199)
      See: box 4, folder 99
    - Williams, George Huntington (9), 1892-1895 (Box 7, Folder 200)
    - Williamson, Edward Higginson (1), 1895 (Box 7, Folder 200)
  - Jane Lathrop Trumbull
    - Dana, Henrietta Francis (Silliman) (2), 1861, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 201)
    - Grimes, Elizabeth Sarah (Nealley) (2), 1861-1862 (Box 7, Folder 201)
    - Silliman, S. J. (1), 1861 (Box 7, Folder 201)
  - Correspondence of Others
    - Cooke, Josiah P. to B. Silliman, Jr. (1), 1860 (Box 7, Folder 202)
    - Cowles, Calvin A. to J. D. Dana (1), 1859 (Box 7, Folder 203)
    - Cutting, Charles W. to J. D. Dana (1), 1866 (Box 7, Folder 203)
    - Domeyko, Ignacio to David Trumbull (1), 1875 (Box 7, Folder 204)
    - Faraday, Michael to John Percy (1), 1855 (Box 7, Folder 205)
    - Ford, William E. to Whitman Cross (1), 1920 (Box 7, Folder 206)
    - Goodman, G. to Robert F. Metzdorf (1), 1900 (Box 7, Folder 207)
    - Gregory, James R. to J. D. Dana (1), 1864 (Box 7, Folder 207)
    - Grout, Frank F. to Whitman Cross (1), 1920 (Box 7, Folder 208)
    - Harriman, S. K. to W. D. Whitney (1) (Box 7, Folder 209)
    - Henry, Joseph to S. W. Johnson (1), 1868 (Box 7, Folder 209)
    - Lea, Isaac to J. D. Dana (2), 1868 (Box 7, Folder 210)
    - Liebig, Justus to Ogden N. Rood (1), 1863 (Box 7, Folder 211)
    - Percy, John to Lee Pattinson (1), 1856 (Box 7, Folder 212)
    - Robinson, Henry H. to Whitman Cross (1), 1920 (Box 7, Folder 213)
    - Trumbull, James H. to Lyman Trumbull (1), 1862 (Box 7, Folder 214)
    - Tyndall, John to Barker (1), undated (Box 7, Folder 215)
    - Washington, Henry S. to Charles P. Berkey (1), 1932 (Box 7, Folder 216)
    - Way, Francis R. to treasurer of Yale (1), 1862 (Box 7, Folder 217)
    - Wayland, [Franz?) to E. Zschau, 1868 (Box 7, Folder 217)
    - Wiley, W. O. to Whitman Cross (1), 1920 (Box 7, Folder 218)
    - Williams, Edward H. to E. S. Dana (1), 1895 (Box 7, Folder 218)
    - Unidentified (3), 1852, 1860 (Box 7, Folder 219)
- Special Files, 1834-1883, 1891, 1893, 1897-1912, 1916, 1920, undated; Series II; 1'(3 boxes) One folio
  The material in the SPECIAL FILES is grouped into five subsections as follows: George Jarvis Brush, Sarah Jarvis (Brush) McLaughlin, Eliza Trumbull (Brush) Pirsson, Louis Valentine Pirsson, and Jane Lathrop Trumbull.
  Within each of these sections the material is arranged alphabetically by category.
  - George Jarvis Brush
    - Account books of Jarvis Brush (1797-1883), 1834-1866, 1866-1877, 1863-1883 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Biographical sketch of G.J. Brush, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Charts of chemical apparatus, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Lectures on chemistry, 1853 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    - Lectures-notes on chemistry, 1858, 1860 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Lectures - notes on burning fluids experiment, 1859 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Lectures - notes on geology and metallurgy, 1861 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Lectures - notes on metallurgy and mineralogy, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Memoranda re: metallurgy, [1858?] (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Memoranda re: chemistry department of Sheffield Scientific School, 1886 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Memoranda re: Brush position in Sheffield Scientific School, 1873, 1893 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Memoranda re: mineral specimens, 1854, 1864, 1859 (Box 8, Folder 14-15)
    - Notebook: von Pettenkoffer's Diatetisch Physicalische Chemie, 1854 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Personal papers and honors. (Box 8, Folder 17)
      See also: Folio
    - Photographs of G. J. Brush, [1897] (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Preliminary roll of Sheffield Scientific School (1846-1869) with notes by G.J. Brush, 1870 (Box 8, Folder 19)
      (Removed to the Yale Call Number Books)
    - Printed material-miscellaneous, 1851, 1860, 1862-1864, 1868, 1876, 1880, 1891, 1912, 1916, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Report on "Barbours" lead mine (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Sarah Jarvis (Brush) McLaughlin
    - Essay on Dante by E.T. McLaughlin, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Scrapbook compiled by E.T. McLaughlin, 1855-1881 (Box 9, Folder 22, Reel 1U)
      See: Film HM 143. Original volumes discarded, 1982 Sep.
      This folder now contains items from scrapbooks that were not discarded.
    - Scrapbook compiled by Sarah Jarvis (Brush) McLaughlin, 1897-1912 (Reel 1)
    - Memoranda on Brush letter files, undated (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Notebooks on French art, 1896, undated (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Notebooks on Italian art, 1895 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Notes on Italian art, undated (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Louis Valentine Pirsson
    - Autobiographical notes, [1906] (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Biographies re: Pirsson, 1920, undated (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Diary of trip to International Geological Conference, 1897 (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Diary of trip to the Gaspé and Saguenay, 1907 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Identification card from Heidelberg University, 1891 (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Manuscript: "Geology of the Shonkin Sag and Palisade Butte Laccoliths in the Highwood Mountains of Montana" by W.H. Weed and L.V. Pirsson, undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Manuscript: Textbook of Petrography (unfinished), chapters 1 - 3, [1918] (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - Manuscript: Textbook of Petrography (unfinished), Part II and illustrations, [1918] (Box 10, Folder 35)
    - Map of Newport, Rhode Island with notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 36)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Jane Lathrop Trumbull
    - Poem: "The Ballade of Miles Standish" (in hand of Jane Lathrop Trumbull), undated (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Genealogical materials on the Brush and Trumbull families (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous newspapers clippings (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - Miscellaneous Yale programs (Box 10, Folder 41)
- Oversize
  - Folio: Personal papers and honors (Box 11)